Guide to the Harold Lamport Autograph Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harold Lamport autograph collection
1585-1940
MS 731
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(1 folio)
A collection of approximately eighty autograph letters and documents, primarily by European and American political, diplomatic and military figures of the seventeenth through the nineteenth centuries. Notable among them are Napoléon I, Andrew Jackson, Giuseppe Garibaldi, William Gladstone, and Lajos Kossuth.
Lamport, Harold, 1908-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harold Lamport and Mrs. H. L. Friedman, 1961.
Scope and Contents
This autograph collection consists of approximately eighty letters and documents signed primarily by European and American political, diplomatic, and military figures of the seventeenth through nineteenth centuries, including Giuseppe Garibaldi, William Gladstone, Andrew Jackson, Lajos Kossuth, and Napoléon I. The items are arranged in alphabetical order by author. The collection was given to Yale University in 1961 by Harold Lamport and Mrs. H. L. Friedman.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Autographs
- Inventory, 1585-1940, undated; 1.5; (1 box)
  - Abercromby, Sir Ralph, 1734-1801: order for payment to Lt.-Col. Maitland, 1799 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abrantes, [Andoche Junot, duc de, 1771-1813?]: ANS to master of ceremonies at Lisbon, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848: signed poem addressed to H. Silliman Root, 1839 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873: signed ms notes of contribution to The Natural History of the United States, 1861 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aguesseau, _______: ALS to unidentified, 1898 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aubert-Dubayet, Jean-Baptiste-Annibal, 1759-1797; order to the Armée des Côtes de Cherbourg; with engraved portrait, 1795 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bache, Richard, 1737-1811: ALS to Gurden Saltenstall, 1776 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bancroft, Major Ebenezer: orders to Capt. Reuben Butterfield, 1779 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [Bazaine, François-Achille, 1811-1888?]: orders to troops in Mexico, 1864 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beale & Cooper: LS to Samuel Storke, 1734/1735 February 19, 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beauharnais, Eugène, prince d'Eichstätt, 1781-1824: ANS; with engraved portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Belle-Isle, Charles Louis Auguste Fouquet, duc de, 1684-1761: LS, 1744 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Berthier, Louis Alexandre, 1752/1753-1815: LS to Napoléon I, emperor of the French, with annotations by Napoléon, 1812 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Biron, Armand Louis de Gontaut, duc de Lauzun, 1747-1793: LS to unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bonaparte, Jérôme Napoléon, 1805-1870.: LS to unnamed general; with printed caricature from Figaro, 1874 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brinkley, Frank, 1841-1912: ALS to Mr. Millet, [189?] April 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Buchanan, James, 1791-1868: LS to George P. Morris, 1858 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Burbeck, Henry, 1754-1848: ALS to Thomas Cushing; with printed portrait, 1803 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836: bank order, printed form signed, 1788 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Burrall, Jonathan: ALS to Daniel Delozier, 1792 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Carleton, Henry Boyle, d. 1725: MS order to Charles Montague to pay Alexander Stanhope, 1700 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Castries, Armand Charles Augustin, 1756-1842: ANS to unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chase, Salmon Portland, 1803-1873: LS to John Hickman; ALS to Mr. Johnson, 1863 January 22, 1866 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Christie, Gabriel: order to George Ross to pay Thomas Bullock, 1769 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Clay, Henry, 1777-1852: LS recommending Waldemard Mentelle, 1817 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908: ALS to James B. Richardson; with engraved portrait, 1889 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Colbert, Jean Baptiste, 1619-1683: letter in the hand of a secretary and printed letter to Cardinal Mazarin; with engraved portrait, 1669 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Colepeper, Thomas, 1637-1708: DS, 1683 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cone, William Russell, 1810-1890: ALS to the Republican Committee of Hartford, Ct., 1873 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Crillon-Mahon, Louis de Berton des Balbes de Quiers, duc de, 1718-1796: LS to Kuhlt, Grelet, et comp.e, 1789 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cuyler, Theodore Ledyard, 1822-1909: ALS to unidentified, 1860 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Davenport, John, 1752-1830: ALS to unidentified, 1801 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dearborn, Henry, 1751-1829: ALS to Erastus Granger, 1804 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Delacrois, Ch.
    General
    See: Prussia. Legation. France box 1 folder 69
  - DeLancey, Oliver, 1718-1785: orders to DeLancey's 3rd Batallion; with additional note from Col. Arch. Hamilton, 1779 July 10, 14 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - de Sandos Rollin, Alphonse
    See: box 1 folder 69
  - Dorchester, Sir Guy Carleton, 1st baron, 1724-1808: LS to Alex Adair; LS to Executive Officers of His Majesty's Ordnance, 1790 June 1, 1791 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Eugène, prince of Savoie-Carignan, 1663-1736: LS to unidentified, 1721 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, 1692-1782: deed for land granted to George Mason, 1767 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Finley, James E. B.: ALS to Mason F. Cogswell, 1783 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Fox, H.
    See: Great Britain. Sovereigns box 1 folder 49
  - France. Conseil du roi: "Rolle des sommes que Le Roy lu son Conseil veut et ordonne payees...", 1789 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - France. Ministère des affaires etrangères: letter to M. Mercier, ministère de 1'Empereur à Washington, 1863 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Fürstenberg, Ferdinand von, bp. of Paderborn, 1626-1683: LS to Johann Christoph, provost at Ellwangen, 1663 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Gambetta, Léon Michel, 1838-1882: LS to the "Cassier du Ministère de l'Intérieur", 1870 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Garibaldi, Giuseppe, 1807-1882: ANS to "Caro Croce", 1872 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Gladstone, William Ewart, 1809-1898: ALS to Mrs. Ottley, 1872 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Gloninger, John: ALS to John C. Nicholson, and "Supplementary Return of the exempts of the 1st Brigade, 6th Division of Pennsylvania Militia", 1787 Aug, 1802 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Goddard, Charles: ALS to Mason F. Cogswell, 1814 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - [Great Britain. Army?]: orders for greeting the king, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Great Britain. Customs: bond issued to Edward Wright, master of the "Prince Eugene", by customs officers in London, 1735 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Great Britain. Sovereigns: order to Thomas Winnington, Sir William Yonge and Others, signed "By His Majesty's Command: H. Pelham, H. Fox, G. Lyttleton", 1745 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Grouchy, Emmanuel, marquis de, 1766-1847: LS to Lt.-Gen. Comte Pajor; with engraved portrait, 1835 February 16. (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Guizot, François Pierre Guillaume, 1787-1874: NS to unidentified, 1872 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Halifax, George Montague, earl of, d. 1739: subscription for shares in the stock of the Governor and Company of Merchants of Great Britain Trading to the South Seas, printed form signed, 1720 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Hamilton, Arch.
    See: box 1 folder 34
  - Handfield, William: LS to William Adair, 1759 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Harlan, James, 1820-1899: LS to Abraham Lincoln, 1865 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Hawes, Benjamin: order addressed to Capt. Adams, 1778 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Henri III, king of France, 1551-1589: LS to Seigneur Hipolito; with engraved portrait, 1585 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Hooper, William, 1742-1790: AMS titled "Fellow Citizens", undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Hopson, Peregrine Thomas: "Extract from a Council of War held in the Garrison of Louisbourg, copy in the hand of E. Bradshaw, secy. to the governor,", 1748 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hue, François, 1757-1819: LS, 1810 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895: 2 ALS to Mrs. White, 1876 April 9, 1882 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845: promissory note to Jenkin Whiteside, also signed by James Jackson; 2 pages of ALS to Gen. Richard K. Call, 1820 March 21, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Jackson, James
    See: Andrew Jackson box 1 folder 61
  - Kissam, Elizabeth: ALS to Major Kissam, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Kossuth, Lajos, 1802-1894: autograph and printed portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - London. Trinity House: receipt for duty paid to Edward Wright, master of the "Prince Eugene", 1735 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Lossing, Benson John, 1813-1891: ALS to G. P. Morris, 1855 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Lyttleton, G.
    See: box1 folder 49
  - Monroe, James, 1799-1870: ALS to Daniel Webster, 1841 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Napoléon I, emperor of the French, 1769-1821
    See: box 1 folder 13
  - O'Brien, Richard, 1758-1824: ALS to Consul Eaton, Algiers, 1800 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Pelham, H.
    See: box 1 folder 49
  - Phillimore, Mrs. Lion Fitzpatrick: ALS to Mr. Matersen, 1940 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Prussia. Legation. France: passport issued to Conrad Engelhert Velsner, signed De Sandos Rollin and Ch. Delacrois, 1796 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Richards, W.: ALS to Lt.-Gen. Johnston, 1779 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - St. Vincent, John Jervis, earl of, 1735-1823: autograph and engraved portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Sandwich, John Montague, 4th earl of, 1718-1792: LS to unidentified, 1781 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Spencer, George John Spencer, 2nd earl of, 1758-1834: letter to Henry, Duke of Newcastle, 1782 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Tarente, Etienne Jacques Joseph Macdonald, duc de, 1765-1840: letter of recommendation, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Tenney, Edward Payson, 1835-:ALS to Mrs. Deming, 1878 October 8 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Tryon, William, 1725-1788: official order, "Signals by Day and Night for Long Island and King's Bridge", undated (Box 1, Folder 76)